A Guide to the Louis J. Halle Papers 1941-1995
Special Collections Department, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Louis J. Halle Papers 1941-1995
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
10603-q
ca. 1,000 items (3 Hollinger boxes, 1.5 linear feet)
This addition to the papers of Louis J. Halle, Jr. consists of correspondence with scientists, naturalists, political scientists, magazine and newspaper editors, professors of foreign affairs and international relations, and personal friends, ca. 1941-1995.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
The collection was given to the University of Virginia Library by Louis J. Halle, Jr., Geneva, Switzerland, on December 21, 1995.
Biographical/Historical Information
Louis J. Halle, Jr. (1910- ) is a political scientist, author, philosopher and naturalist.
Scope and Content Information
This addition to the papers of Louis J. Halle, Jr. consists of correspondence with scientists, naturalists, political scientists, magazine and newspaper editors, professors of foreign affairs and international relations, and personal friends, ca. 1941-1995. Subjects mentioned in letters are typed in bold following the name of the correspondents listed below. Also present is the occasional speech or article by Halle, attached to the correspondence. Correspondents include George F. Kennan, Flora Lewis, Paul Nitze, Robert McFarlane, Roger T. Peterson, James Reston, and Urs Schwarz.
Arrangement
Alphabetically arranged in correspondence files
Contents List
- Correspondence: A-B 1979-1995 (Box 1)
  Alice Acheson re the U.S. stamp honoring Dean Acheson
  Prince Sadruddin Aga Khan
  Dr. Aldis
  Henry Allen re his article on Jacqueline Kennedy Onassis
  David Ashford re birds
  Oliver M. Ashford re "the butterfly effect," with a copy of a letter from Edward N. Lorenz
  Faiwzia Assad
  Henry Babel
  Berkshire School, Sheffield, Massachusetts
  David Bird
  Professor Karl E. Birnbaum
  Victor J. Bonilla
  John Tyler Bonner
  Philip Wilson Bonsal re the State Department, Inter-American Division, during World War II
  Daniel Boorstin
  Robert Boyer
  Albert Bressand
  Shirley Briggs re birds and the Audubon Naturalist Society
- Correspondence: Audobon Naturalist Society 1982-1991 (Box 1)
- Corrrespondence: John G. Blair 1982-1985 (Box 1)
- Correspondence: British Birds 1991-1995 (Box 1)
- Correspondence: C 1985-1995 (Box 1)
  Lucius Caflisch re Olmsted fellows
  Peter Calvocoressi
  Faith (Chipman) Parker, including memoirs of two years spent in France, 1922-1923
  Coop Geneve
  Cornell University Press
  Ian C. Craig
- Correspondence: D 1988-1993 (Box 1)
  Kenneth C. Danforth
  Jean Daniel, Director Le Nouvel Observateur
  Dialouge, ed. J. Daniel Philpott
  Dr. & Mrs. Reinhold Drifte
  John Droege re William Vogt
  Frank Dunand
  Roger Dunand
  Freeman Dyson re space colonization
- Correspondence: E-F 1984-1995 (Box 1)
  The Economist
  Dr. John C. Edwards re Otto Max Koischwitz
  Jacques-Simon Eggly
  John Farrenkopf re Oswald Spengler and The Decline of the West
  Dr. Ulrich Finkenzeller
  G. Fournier
  Franklin College, Switzerland speech, "What Future for Mankind?"
  Christoph Frei
  Jacques Freymond
- Correspondence: Patrick Fitzgerald 1977-1991 (Box 1)
  re Chinese history(1977 May 22, Jun 29; 1986 Jan 17; 1989 May 26); Halle's impressions of Hong Kong and India(1987 Apr 4; May 29); the U.S. Presidential election(198[9] Jan 6)
- Correspondence: G 1962-1995 (Box 2)
  Curt Gasteyger
  Paul Geroudet re waterfowl of Geneva(1964 Nov 19)
  Lee A. Gladwin
  Richard Goold-Adams (?-1995) re John Foster Dulles(1962 Dec 27); conditions in Argentina, the Falklands War and Margaret Thatcher(1983 Jan 31; Feb 5; Mar 2 & 18)
  Frederic Grare
  Gertrude N. Green
  Professor A.J.R. Groom
- Correspondence: Harmon H. Gladstone 1941,1961-1993 (Box 2)
  Harmon H. Goldstone and his mother Aline Goldstone re Halle's view of the book of Job in the Bible(1963 May 27, attached letter); Marianne Moore(1975 Feb 18); Otto Max Koischwitz(1975 May 23 & 27); comments re Charles de Gaulle by Dean Acheson(1980 Jul 5 & Sep 8); newclipping obituary of Mildred Gillars, "Axis Sally," and mistress of Otto Max Koischwitz (1988 Jul 4)
- Correspondence: H-I 1974, 1985-1995 (Box 2)
  Peter Halle re obituaries of Roger Halle
  Mrs. Roger Halle re the death of Roger
  Stuart L. Hannon
  David Hartridge re the scarcity of once common birds in Europe and possible causes
  Harvard Magazine
  Mr. Heldring The New Republic
  History Today re environmental history
  Coleman W. Hoyt re funeral oration for Roger Halle
  Thomas L. Hughes, President, Carnegie Endowment for International Peace, including a Trustee's Dinner speech
  John Ivan Huscha
  International Herald Tribune re invasion of Haiti by the United States
  International Institute for Strategic Studies, London
- Correspondence: J-K 1985-1994 (Box 2)
  Maurice Jacob re physics
  Professor Lock K. Johnson
  Kairas Kabraji
  Ambassador Max M. Kampelman, including an article on the "real William Shakespeare" by John B. Fisher (1994 Jul 7)
  Scott Kennedy re environmental history
  Robert A. Klein
- Correspondence: George F. Kennan 1988-1994 (Box 2)
  George F. Kennan (entire folder) re Around the Cragged Hill and his career and the apparent lack of policy planning in the State Department (1994 Aug 28)
- Correspondence: L-M 1980-1995 (Box 2)
  Flora Lewis re her columns in The New York Times
  Les Line
  Eleanor R. Loft
  Lutz Lucker
  Richard B. McAdoo
  Robert C. McFarlane re Halle's memory of him as a student (1989 Mar 31)
  Linda Marion, Johns Hopkins University Bologna Center, including "Memories of One Who Taught at Bologna" by Halle
  Charles Burton Marshall
  Tom Manson
  Ernst Mayr, Museum of Comparative Zoology, Harvard University
  Mary Midgley
  Lorus J. Milne
  Claude Monnier
  David Moorhouse, Halle's son-in-law
- Correspondence: New Scientist 1987-1991 (Box 2)
  New Scientist re nuclear deterrence and including Halle's article "Evolution Unexplained"
- Correspondence: Paul Nitze 1954-1995 (Box 2-3)
  Paul Nitze subjects include: Dean Acheson and the possibility of his giving lectures at the University of Virginia(1954 Sep 20; 1956 Jan 7); the Marshall Plan(1954 Nov 16); "An Evaluation of Allied Strategy" by Nitze (1955 Jun 3); Nitze's remarks concerning Halle's "Strategy versus Ideology"(1956 Jan 7); the use of gas warfare vs nuclear warfare(1958 May 25; Jul 9; 1994 Jan 20); the Soviet Union and the Cold War(1959 Dec 10); the Vietnam War(1967 Aug 26); Nitze's notes re Halle's "Indeterminacy and Purpose"(1974 Dec 22; 1975 Jan 6); Salt II agreement(1979 Nov 5, Dec 9); "Why We Don't Count the French and British Missiles" by Lawrence S. Eagleburger [1983 May 20]; "The Soviet SS-20 Decision" by Raymond L. Garthoff (1983 Jun 8); comments about Nitze's memoirs (1983 Oct 26); Nitze's comments re George Kennan's article in the New York Times(1983 Nov 10); Nitze's speeches at the Woodrow Wilson Center and The Johns Hopkins University(1984 Feb 17); "Strategic Defense Initiative: Its Nature and Rationale" by Nitze (1985 Nov 1; 1986 Jan 7); the question about whether Russia sees itself as more a part of the West or East (1986 Oct 6); "The Evolution of World Politics" by Halle (1988 Sep 20); Mikhail Gorbachev(1988 Oct 3); death of Phyllis Nitze(1987 Jun 28); "The Strong Atlantic Bridge" by Nitze (1990 Feb 20); Nitze's speech at the Inauguration of the new Council on Foreign Relations buildings (1990 Mar 12); "U.S. Strategic Policy as We Enter a New Decade"(1990 Apr 10); "America: An Honest Broker" in Foreign Affairs(Fall 1990); "Inaugural Remarks at the International Petroleum Executive Seminar"(1990 Oct 28); George Marshall and the Marshall Plan(1993 May 14, 31); and President Bill Clinton and foreign policy(1994 Dec 14; 1995 Jan 15).
- Correspondence: O-P 1948, 1986-1995 (Box 3)
  Dr. Malcolm A. Ogilvie re birds
  Dr. Gerard O'Neill
  G. Palthey
  Mary Margaret Patterson
  Lorne Peterson re Spring in Washington
  Roger T. Peterson re birds sighted along the Chesapeake and Ohio Canal, just above the mouth of the Seneca River
  Vladimir Petrosvsky
  Dr. Alberto Martinez Piedra
- Correspondence: R 1986-1993 (Box 3)
  Juan F. Rada re watchmaking and time
  Frank H.T. Rhodes, President of Cornell University, re
  S. Dillon Ripley, Smithsonian
  Lt. General E.L. Rowny, President Alumni Association, National War College
- Correspondence: James B. Reston 1956-1993 (Box 3)
  re Vietnam and the Geneva Conference of 1954(1956 Feb 20 and attached); nuclear vs conventional warfare(1956 Jul 15); the Middle East and the Suez Canal(1957 Jan 24); the Swiss Army(1959 May 6); voting re scientific decisions(1962 Mar 10); John Kennedy(1961 Nov 7;1963 Apr 24); American arms control negotiations(1977 Apr 8); Alexander Haig(1981 Sep 15 & 24); Halle's article, "A Post-mortem on the Libyan Raid"(1986 Apr 24); Contra aid and Oliver North(1987 Jul 24); President Bill Clinton, Haiti and Somalia(1993 Dec 1)
- Correspondence: S 1985-1995 (Box 3)
  William Safire
  Professor Thomas J. Schoenbaum re a biography of Dean Rusk
  Scientific American
  Guy-Olivier Segond, Mayor of Geneva
  Jeremy B. Shearer, Permanent Representative, South African Mission re morality in foreign policy
  Dr. Edwin M. Shook re Guatemala and archaeology
  Smithsonian Symposium "Man and Beasts Revisited" including Halle's article, "Lift Up Your Eyes - Our Future in Space"
  Carol Sotelli
  George E. Stuart, Archeology Editor, National Geographic Society
  Alexander Swoboda, Director The Graduate Institute of International Studies
  Jean Swoyer
- Correspondence: Urs Schwarz 1985-1995 (Box 3)
  the Swiss army(1989 May 3); the death of Richard Goold-Adams(1995 Apr 19)
- Correspondence: T 1986-1994 (Box 3)
  Television Suisse Romande
  Dr. W.L.N. Tickell re albatrosses
  Times Literary Supplement
  Julio de la Torre re owls
  Touring Club Suisse
  Trees for the Future
  D.A. Turner
- Correspondence: U-V 1984-1993 (Box 3)
  The Voluntary Euthanasia Society of Scotland re hemlock
  Astrid Watanabe
  Alexander Watson
  Dr. Steven Weinberg
  Wellesley College, Wellesley, Massachusetts
  Dr. Randall White
- Correspondence: Virginia Quarterly Review 1987-1992 (Box 3)
  Halle's "Appendix on the Changing Social Attitudes towards Sexual Relations"(1987 Nov 29) and several Clovis articles by Halle (1987)